Guide to the Harvey Shapiro Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Harvey Shapiro papers
1923-1993
YCAL MSS 604
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.17
(6 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the personal and professional life of American poet and editor Harvey Shapiro. Correspondence consists chiefly of letters to Shapiro from American and English-language authors, literary critics, and editors who came of age in the post-WWII period. There are files for Barbara Gibbs and Francis Golffing and for author and publisher Alan Swallow, but letters can also be found for Charles Bernstein, Allen Ginsberg, David Ignatow, Robert Lowell, George Oppen, and others. Many letters from writers are addressed to Shapiro in his capacity as editor of The New York Times Magazine or The New York Times Book Review. The Writings series contains writings by Shapiro, material relating to work by Shapiro, such as publicity and reviews, and writings by others. Shapiro's writings feature drafts for a number of poetry collections, including Lauds and Nightsounds (1978), The Light Holds (1984), National Cold Storage Company (1988), and This World (1971), as well as shorter works. The writings by others may have been solicited by or submitted to Shapiro in his capacity as editor and separated from accompanying correspondence. Personal papers include clippings and programs, financial and legal records, and a small number of photographs.
Shapiro, Harvey, 1924-2013
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Harvey Shapiro on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Harvey Shapiro (1924-)
Harvey Shapiro, an American poet, was born in Chicago, Illinois on 27 January 1924. He served in the U.S. Air Force from 1943 to 1945 and was educated at Yale University (BA, 1947) and Columbia University (MA, 1948). Shapiro taught briefly as an English instructor before embarking on a career as an editor, first with Commentary (1955-1956) and The New Yorker (1956-1957), and later with The New York Times Magazine (1957-1975, 1983-) and The New York Times Book Review (1975-1983). Shapiro's collections of poetry include This World (1971), Lauds & Nightsounds (1978), The Light Holds (1984), and National Cold Storage Company (1988). Shapiro married Edna Lewis Kaufman in 1953 and has two sons.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the personal and professional life of American poet and editor Harvey Shapiro. Correspondence consists chiefly of letters to Shapiro from American and English-language authors, literary critics, and editors who came of age in the post-WWII period, with the bulk of the letters dating from the 1950s through mid 1980s. There are files for Barbara Gibbs and Francis Golffing and for author and publisher Alan Swallow, but letters can also be found for Charles Bernstein, Allen Ginsberg, David Ignatow, Robert Lowell, George Oppen, and others. Many letters from writers are addressed to Shapiro in his capacity as editor of The New York Times Magazine or The New York Times Book Review. Letters from editors of other journals tend to concern his own literary submissions.
The Writings series contains writings by Shapiro, material relating to work by Shapiro, such as publicity and reviews, and writings by others. Shapiro's writings feature drafts for a number of poetry collections, including Lauds & Nightsounds (1978), The Light Holds (1984), National Cold Storage Company (1988), and This World (1971), as well as shorter works. The writings by others may have been solicited by or submitted to Shapiro in his capacity as editor and separated from accompanying correspondence.
Personal papers include clippings and programs, financial and legal records, and a small number of photographs.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1923-1985. II. Writings, 1954-1993. III. Other Materials, 1931-1989.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Editors -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Bernstein, Charles, 1950-; Gibbs, Barbara, 1912-1993; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997; Golffing, Francis; Ignatow, David, 1914-1997; Lowell, Robert, 1917-1977; Oppen, George, 1908-1984; Shapiro, Harvey, 1924-2013; Swallow, Alan, 1915-1966
- Correspondence, 1923-1985; Series I; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by name.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence consists chiefly of letters to Shapiro from American and English-language authors, literary critics, and editors who came of age in the post-WWII period, with the bulk of the letters dating from the 1950s through mid 1980s. There are larger files for Barbara Gibbs and Francis Golffing and for author and publisher Alan Swallow, but letters can also be found for Charles Bernstein, Allen Ginsberg, David Ignatow, Robert Lowell, George Oppen, and others. Many letters from writers are addressed to Shapiro in his capacity as editor of the The New York Times Magazine or The New York Times Book Review (1975-1983). Letters from editors of other journals, on the other hand, tend to concern his own literary submissions. The odd incoming letter is accompanied by an autograph manuscript note by Shapiro or a carbon reply. Enclosures, identified below in folder notes, include drafts of writings, third-party correspondence, photographs, and printed material.
  - Vendor list, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Asher, Aaron, 1983 September 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Atheneum, 1962 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bank Street College of Education, 1964 August 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Barnard, Mary, 1961 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 1980 November (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Belitt, Ben, 1949-1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes letters to Edna Shapiro
  - Berger, Thomas, 1983 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bernstein, Charles, 1985 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bishop, Elizabeth, 1965 April 9 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Botteghe Oscvre, 1957 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Botsford, Keith; Botsford, Ann, 1948-1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Braude, Benjamin, 1984 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Brown, Rita Mae, 1983 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes copies of reviews
  - Brown, Robert McAfee, 1983 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Buckely, William F., 1983 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Burnshaw, Stanley, 1962 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Carruth, Hayden, 1968 August 26 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Carter, Jimmy, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ciardi, John, 1954, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Coetzee, J. M., 1985 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Commentary, 1957 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cowley, Malcolm, 1978, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Includes copy of poem
  - The Cummington Press, 1949-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Includes printed ephemera and draft of poem
  - Davenport, Guy, 1983 June 4 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Donald, David Herbert, 1983 September 5 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Donoghue, Denis, 1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Includes review of Yeats and American Poetry by Terence Diggory
  - DuPlessis, Rachel Blau, 1983 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Eberhart, Richard, 1951, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Elias, Robert Henry, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Fielde, Rolf, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Fowlie, Wallace, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Frankel, Max, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Gallant, Mavis, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Gilliatt, Penelope, 1983 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Ginsberg, Allen, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Gold, Herbert, 1983 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Golffing, Barbara Gibbs; Golffing, Francis, 1949-1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 38-40)
    Includes drafts of writings, photographs, and clipping
  - Goodenough, Erwin Ramsdell, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Graves, Robert, 1977 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Hall, Donald, 1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Harrigan, Anthony, 1947 August 22 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Harris, Mark, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Helga Greene Literary Agency, 1957 July 17 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Herschberger, Ruth, 1951-1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Hoagland, Edward, 1983 November 30 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Holmes, John, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Incldues printed ephemera
  - Horizon, 1947 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Humphrey, William, 1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Ignatow, David; Ignatow, Rose Grabart, 1954-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Includes copies of poems
  - Intercultural Publications Inc., 1955 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Jewish National and University Library, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Jordan, June, 1982 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Kazan, Alfred, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Kenner, Hugh, 1983 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Kinnell, Galway, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Knowles, John, 1983 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Kostelanetz, Richard, 1978 December 24 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Ladies' Home Journal, 1954 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Library of Congress, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Lindbergh, Charles, 1972 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Lish, Gordon, 1985 July (Box 1, Folder 64)
    Includes letter to Lish from Anne Tyler
  - Lockwood Memorial Library, 1954 March 9 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Longo, Lucas, undated (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Lowell, Robert, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    Includes letter from Lowell to Elliott Coleman
  - MacLeish, Archibald, [1923?] (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Midstream, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Mineka, Francis, 1952 June 28 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Morgan, Ted, [1983] September 15 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Moynihan, Daniel P., 1970 March 16 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - The Nation, 1955 October 18 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - New Directions Publishing Corp., 1956-1984 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - The New Leader, 1958 March 5 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - New Mexico Quarterly, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - New York Times Book Review, 1952, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Oates, Joyce Carol, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Oppen, George, 1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Ozick, Cynthia, 1971-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Paideuma, 1980 March 20 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Palmer, Michael, 1983 July 5 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Partisan Review, 1952 August 2 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Poetry, 1956-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - The Poetry Center, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - The Poets' Theatre, 1956 February 8 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - The Provincial, 1956 April 4 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Putnam, Clay; Putnam, Maureen, 1953-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Quennell, Peter, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Rakosi, Carl, 1975 October 6 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Reznikoff, Charles, 1971 June 27 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - The Rockefeller Foundation, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Salisbury, Harrison E., 1983 September 24 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Saroyan, William, 1976 July 20 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Schell, Orville, 1983 April 15 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Schlesinger, Arthur M. (Arthur Meier), 1977 June 23 (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Schwartz, Howard, 1977 February 21 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Seidman, Hugh, 1968 July 31 (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Shattuck, Roger, 1953-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 99)
    Includes poems
  - Simpson, Louis, 1956, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Sklarew, Myra, 1984 January 10 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Stark, Irwin, 1963 May (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Stewart, Roy H., 1964 December 28 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Swallow, Alan, 1949-1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 104-105)
  - Swenson, May, 1954-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Syrkin, Marie, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Tate, Allen, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Thoby-Marcelin, Philippe, 1950 November 24 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Towers, Robert, 1983 September 19 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - University of Virginia, 1984 September 20 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - Updike, John, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Viereck, Peter, 1950, undated (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - Voices, 1955, undated (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - Wakefield, Dan, undated (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - Wakoski, Diane, 1982 September 30 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Walt Disney Productions, 1957 September 20 (Box 2, Folder 117)
  - Weiss, Ted, 1954-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - Wesleyan University Press, 1970 August 17 (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - White, Katharine S., 1957 March 21 (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - Whitman, Ruth, 1982 December 29 (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - Who's Who in World Jewry, 1955 May 9 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - Williams, Jonathan, 1965-1983 (Box 2, Folder 123)
    Includes copy of third-party letter from Williams, photograph, and printed ephemera
  - Wimsatt, William K., 1956 August 19 (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - Woods, John, 1951 January 15 (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - Yale University. Ezra Stiles College, 1978 September 21 (Box 2, Folder 126)
  - Zukofsky, Celia Thaew, 1978 June 14 (Box 2, Folder 127)
  - First name only, 1949-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 128)
  - Others and unidentified, 1950-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 129)
  - Third-party correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 130)
  - Empty folders, undated (Box 2, Folder 131)
- Writings, 1954-1993; Series II; 1.05; (3 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Writings by Harvey Shapiro and Writings by Others.
  Series II. Writings contains writings by Shapiro, material relating to work by Shapiro, such as publicity and reviews, and writings by others. Shapiro's writings feature drafts for a number of poetry collections, including Lauds & Nightsounds (1978), The Light Holds (1984), National Cold Storage Company (1988), and This World (1971), as well as shorter works. The writings by others may have been solicited by or submitted to Shapiro in his capacity as editor and separated from accompanying correspondence.
  Additional writings by Shapiro can be found in the clippings file in Series III.
  - Writings by Harvey Shapiro
    - Battle Report: Selected Poems, reviews, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 132-133)
    - "Bylines", 1961-1984, undated (Box 3, Folder 134)
    - [Interview], New York Public Library, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 135)
    - "Isaac Bashevis Singer Introduction," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 136)
    - "Joel," essay, typescript, [circa 1986] (Box 3, Folder 137-138)
      Includes correspondence, autograph notes, and printed ephemera
    - Lauds & Nightsounds, drafts, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 139-141)
    - The Light Holds, draft, typescript, and page proof, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 142)
    - The Light Holds, draft, typescript, and page proof, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 143-144)
    - Mountain Fire, Thornbush, publicity and reviews, 1955-1963 (Box 4, Folder 145)
    - National Cold Storage Company, draft, proofs, book jackets, publicity, and reviews, 1988, undated (Box 4, Folder 146-149)
    - [Poems], typescript and printed versions, undated (Box 4, Folder 150)
    - "Remembering Charles Reznikoff," essay, typescript, corrected (photocopy), undated (Box 4, Folder 151)
    - Review, The Eye by John Holmes, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 152)
    - Review, Kaddish and Other Poems by Allen Ginsberg, drafts, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 153)
    - This World, contract, draft, typescript, reviews, 1970-1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 154-157)
    - Tributes to David Ignatow, printed versions, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 158)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 5, Folder 159)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 5, Folder 160)
  - Writings by Others
    - Barth, John
      - "Some Reasons Why I Tell the Stories...", typescript, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 161)
    - Bernstein, Charles
      - "Pounding Fascism," essay, typescript, [circa 1984] (Box 5, Folder 162)
    - Holmes, John
      - [Poems], typescript and printed version, 1954, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 163)
    - Hoskins, Katherine
      - [Poems], typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 164)
        Includes ANS dated 1949
    - Miller, Walter James
      - "Z: In Memory of Louis Zukofsky," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 165)
    - Moore, Marianne
      - "Christmas," [story?], typescript (copy), corrected, 1960 November 18 (Box 5, Folder 166)
    - Pawel, Ernst
      - "Kafka at 100," essay, draft, typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 167)
    - Quennell, Peter
      - Book review, White Mischief by James Fox, autograph manuscript and printout, 1983, undated (Box 5, Folder 168)
    - Rowse, A. L. (Alfred Leslie)
      - "Towards a Modern Shakespeare," essay, typescript (photocopy), undated (Box 5, Folder 169)
    - Swenson, May
      - [Poems], typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 170)
        Includes cover letter dated 1950
    - Washburn, Katharine
      - [Introduction?], typescript, signed, undated (Box 5, Folder 171)
    - White, Edmund
      - Book review, The Cannibal Galaxy by Cynthia Ozick, typescript (photocopy), 1983 (Box 5, Folder 172)
        Includes cover letter
    - Wimsatt, William K.
      - Book review, printed version, reprint, undated (Box 5, Folder 173)
- Personal Papers, 1931-1998; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series III. Personal Papers contains other material relating to Shapiro. Materials include clippings and programs, financial and legal records, and a small number of photographs.
  - Clippings, 1952-1998, undated (Box 5, Folder 174)
  - Contracts and legal records, 1960-1986 (Box 5, Folder 175)
  - Discharge certificate, 1931 June 20 (Box 5, Folder 176)
  - Drawing, 1989 January 27 (Box 5, Folder 177)
  - Empty folder, undated (Box 5, Folder 178)
  - Financial records, 1982-1983, undated (Box 5, Folder 179)
  - Photographs, 1950s, undated (Box 5, Folder 180)
  - Programs, 1950-1979, undated (Box 5, Folder 181-182)
- Oversize, 0.08; (1 box)
  - Battle Report, reviews (In Series II), 1967 (Box 6 oversize, Folder 183)
  - "Bylines," clipping (In Series II), 1961 January 15 (Box 6 oversize, Folder 184)
  - Mountain Fire, Thornbush, publicity and reviews (In Series II), 1955-1963 (Box 6 oversize, Folder 185)
  - National Cold Storage Company, proof (In Series II), 1988 (Box 6 oversize, Folder 186)
  - This World, reviews (In Series II), 1971 (Box 6 oversize, Folder 187)
  - Clippings (In Series III), 1958-1998, undated (Box 6 oversize, Folder 188)
  - Programs (In Series III), 1966, undated (Box 6 oversize, Folder 189)